<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the late reverend and learned John Owen D.D. by a friendly scrutiny into the merits, and manner of Mr. Rich. Baxters opposition to twelve arguments concerning worship by the lyturgy, said to be Dr. Owens / by a hearty friend to all good men, and of the unity of the spirit in the bond of peace.</title>
            <author>Hearty friend to all good men.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17356609</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17356609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1106:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the late reverend and learned John Owen D.D. by a friendly scrutiny into the merits, and manner of Mr. Rich. Baxters opposition to twelve arguments concerning worship by the lyturgy, said to be Dr. Owens / by a hearty friend to all good men, and of the unity of the spirit in the bond of peace.</title>
                  <author>Hearty friend to all good men.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A friendly scrutiny into the grounds of Mr. Richard Baxters treatment of Dr. John Owen deceased, and the manner of it, in his examination of twelve arguments, never printed; but, according to Mr. Baxters title of his book, said to be Dr. Owens. In a letter to Mr. Baxter ... "--Caption, p. 1.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Catholick communion defended against both extreams.</term>
               <term>Owen, John, 1616-1683.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106428:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION Of the Late Reverend and Learned <hi>John Owen D. D.</hi> BY A Friendly Scrutiny Into the Merits, and Manner of Mr. <hi>Rich. Baxters</hi> Oppoſition to Twelve Arguments concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Worſhip by the Lyturgy, ſaid to be Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a hearty Friend to all good Men, and of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Detrahere, vel detrahentem audire; quod horum damnabilius, non facile dixerim.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Rumor res ſine teſte, ſine judice, maligna, fallax.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Malthus,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:106428:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106428:2"/>
            <head>A Friendly Scrutiny into the Grounds of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxters</hi> Treatment of Dr. <hi>John Owen</hi> deceaſed, and the manner of it, in his Examination of twelve Arguments, never Printed; but, according to Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Title of his Book, <hi>ſaid</hi> to be Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi> In a Letter to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> by a lover of all good Men, and a hearty Friend to the <hi>Unity of the Spirit, in the bond of Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have ſome months ſince ſeen divers ſmall manuſcripts in the hands of ſeveral private Perſons, containing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt ſome Mens attending to the Worſhip of God by the Liturgy, under their preſent Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and ſaid to be Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi> I read over moſt part of one of them, but I not apprehending in them that Accuracy, and cloſe arguing, as ſuited the well known abilities, and printed works of that Pious, and learned Author; concluded they were not his: or (at leaſt) not the products of his Induſtry, nor intended by him for a publick view. And this was not my Opinion alone, but the ſenſe of others, both of greater, and leſſer latitude in the points controverted therein.</p>
            <p>The firſt reports I had of your undertaking to expoſe, and confute them in Print, as Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> upon <hi>hear-ſay,</hi> was to me (all Circumſtances conſidered) ſomewhat of ſurprize, though not altogether increadible. Yet I hoped your Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would obtain the aſcendant of any inclination of your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106428:3"/>own, or motions from others to ſuch a task: It being your often repeated advice, that in things Lawful, yea, ſometimes Duties; we are to conſider whether they will do more good, or hurt; and accordingly to act, or deſiſt.</p>
            <p>But the thing is done; whether well, or ill. And I have found it in the hands of divers Perſons of Quality, to whom you ſent them, and from whom I perceive you are likely to have no great return of thanks, nor do I find it well reliſhed by many of thoſe, who bear a ſpecial reſpect to your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and are of the ſame ſentiments with you in the latitude of private Mens Communion with the Parochial Aſſemblies. <hi>But let every Man prove his own work,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Dear, and truly Reverend Sir (for ſuch the real Affection, and value I have for you, moves me to ſtile you) I beg of you to reflect again on this Action, and conſider if it ſavour of that Evangelical Love, Union, Peaceableneſs, and Wiſdom, which you have profeſſed (and I believe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely) ſo great a Zeal for. Sir, I need not tell you for your information (but it may be you need a remembrancer) that in the beſt of Men, private, and ſinful Paſſions may joyn with holy Affection, and ſerve their ends by it, and upon it: and that, where holy Zeal, a ſtirring nature, ſtrong Parts, and an exuberant invention, and elocution are one mans proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; a double Caution and warineſs is more than needful: and ſuch often overdo, ſeldom the Contrary. And (to ſpeak my thoughts freely) I believe that as this ill circumſtanced Action of yours is matter of grief to ſeriousholy Perſons of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering perſuaſions, (as to the points agitated by you) of ſport, and ſcorn to haters of all Religion, and Godlineſs in truth: ſo upon the whole it may make work for your own Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>I have had the advantage of ſome Perſonal Acquaintance with the worthy, &amp; Reverend Doctor you preſume you oppoſe, and alſo with your ſelf: And I have that veneration for you both, that I cannot be inſenſible of what concerns either, much leſs of what concerns both in ſo high a degree. And had the Doctor, ſurviving you, trampled on your Grave, and taken ſuch unequal advantages againſt your good Name, and Principles, as you have done of his; I ſhould have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106428:3"/>the ſame obligation, and inclination to embalm your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and adventured my going leſs in his reſpects for my pains.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend in what follows, to maintain againſt you, that it is unlawful to uſe a from of Prayer, or comply with an impoſed Lyturgy, or under ſome circumſtances to joyn in the uſe of ours in Worſhip. For beſide the hazard he expoſes himſelf to, who aſſaults ſuch an armed Intereſt: Enough has been written <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>contra,</hi> already to inform, and it may be to tire any Reader, who knows what to do with his time: beſides, the torrent of violence and fear, or anger, its effects, ſcarce leaves men freedom, and quiet enough for a due, and rational weighing what is written.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall I undertake to juſtify altogether the 12 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments you have Printed as Dr. <hi>Owens,</hi> in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing them. If you had had a mind to be doing with them, nakedly as Arguments; ſuch as they are, better or worſe; without intereſting in them the Reverend deceaſed Doctors Name: You might have done your pleaſure, and diſpleaſed no body that I know of: at leaſt not caſt ſuch a dead fly into the precious Ointment of the name of that worthy Perſon, whom your Charity places in Heaven, and whoſe memory notwithſtanding, will be precious with the Saints on Earth.</p>
            <p>But that which I propoſed to my ſelf was, according to my ſmall Prudence, and weak Abilities, Firſt, to ſignify to your ſelf, and therein to others, whom by expoſing that work ſo, you have intereſted in it, that there was neither Reaſon nor Juſtice in Printing, and Printing againſt thoſe Arguments as Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi> Nor (all Circumſtances conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) a complyance with that Honour, Love, and Tenderneſs, mutually due, eſpecially from Perſons of your, and the Doctors Station, and Circumſtances, while living; much more from the ſurviving to the dead.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the reaſons you oppoſe, (be they whoſe they will) are not altogether ſo tardy, and contemptible, as you make them ſeem to be. And ſeeing you were reſolved they, and the Doctors Name ſhould run the Gantelope toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and their weakneſs be your Weapon to wound him; a little Weapon Salve may contribute to the cure of his good Name by way of Sympathy.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106428:4"/>
            <p> And Reverend Sir, if I ſhall let fall any thing in what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that is contrary to that Reſpect I profeſs to bear to you, I can ſay it in truth, that it is not only beſide, but againſt my intention; and if I can eſpy it, when done, it ſhall ſuffer a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Manuſcript of Arguments which you profeſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, you all along ſuperſcribe D. <hi>O.</hi> to each Argument, which is enough to entitle him to them as their Author pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, in common ſenſe. Although all the ground you give for ſo doing, is, that they are <hi>ſaid</hi> to be his, which you ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in your Title Page.</p>
            <p>Dear Sir, do you not know that the world is full of Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, and the better part of Men ſubject to many miſtakes, and not only innocent, but very hurtful, and injurious ones too. Concluſions are too often meer, or ungrounded gueſſes, and they that carry on ſuch miſtakes, are partakers in the imprudence, and the evil Conſequences alſo, which they put out of their power to cure.</p>
            <p>You ſay Sir, of a Book you reply to, bound up with this, that it is fam'd to be Mr. <hi>Ralphſons,</hi> and upon that ground proceed to cenſure him accordingly. Whereas his <hi>Jury</hi> (who could not be ſuppoſed partially indulgent, and who had all the Evidences that could be procured, to prove Mr. <hi>Ralph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the Author, and improved by the Bench, and Impleaders, to that end to the utmoſt) durſt not from common Fame, nor that particular evidence they had, find him the Author, and thereby expoſe him to the penalties. But Sir, you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not ſuch particular evidence to father theſe on the Dr. but only that 'tis <hi>ſaid;</hi> Your proceeds thereon are therefore more groundleſs, and the cenſures, and reflections you write upon his duſt much more uncharitable.</p>
            <p>But if it be inquired by whom it was ſaid? So far as your Print pretends to (which I ſuppoſe hath made report of your beſt evidence, your wiſdom being ſeldom wanting to your intereſt in ſuch caſes) it was by an <hi>unknown Author of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to you lately ſent: Title to the Letter Printed, with Mr.</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>piece now Conſidered.</hi> In the ſecond line of that Letter, <hi>which you ſay was Dr.</hi> Owens, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. (Alſo ſome of the Doctors Friends, who, or how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106428:4"/>many, or what grounds they had for ſo ſaying, is yet a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.) What poor Evidence was this, to fix ſo faulty a work (as you your ſelf repreſent it) upon ſo worthy a Perſon? But although your Informers Perſon was unknown to you, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what you knew of him according to your Letter printed. And though it may ſeem enough to object, that the Book was printed off, before the Letter of this Perſon unknown, came to your hands, (or the other Chode you for anſwering) and this report could not be the Evidence on which you procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. To this I ſay, that then, for ought it appears, your Evidence was leſs then any ones; who did affirm it to be Dr. <hi>Owens,</hi> except common Fame? And, <hi>non emibus &amp; non appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus eadem eſt ratio.</hi> Moreover, when you had his Letter, and obſerved ſuch a poſitive reporter of the Manuſcripts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctors, to be ſuch an injurious frequent miſtaker againſt your ſelf; and in his reports to your ſelf: it had been enough to perſuade you to put a ſtop to the diſperſing of the Book; leſt that affirmation ſhould prove a miſtake alſo. And O that we were arrived to that practical juſtice, as to be as ſenſible of injuries done to others as to our ſelves, and as careful to avoid having any hand in them! You ſay in your printed Letter to this Informer line 14. <hi>But your miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation tells me the pitiful caſe of moſt in the world. Your honeſt reproofs are founded on abundance of untrue conceits: There are about twenty untruths, through miſtake in matter of Fact, in your Letter; and how groſs are many of them?</hi> I ſhall leave the inferences from theſe words of yours to your own ingenuity.</p>
            <p>But let it be ſuppoſed that the Doctor had written ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what called Arguments againſt Liturgical Worſhip; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it to ſome private Perſon or Perſons in his own hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing. Could this be ſufficient ground for you to print your Manuſcript Copy, and deal ſo ſeverely with it? Worthy Sir, I conceive, and not raſhly; that it is poſſible, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable there might be many variations in the tranſcribing, which it may be was done by many hands, and thoſe none of the moſt exact: and by that time your Copy had its being, as unlike the Autograph, as a Boys Scribble is to an Artiſts Copy. And Sir, You know that every fair Antagoniſt will examine the Printers Errata, e're he will preſume to underſtand the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106428:5"/>ſenſe of the Author examined, and to be oppoſed: which, how you could do here, let any diſcreet Perſon judge.</p>
            <p>And if it be granted yet farther, that the Copy you Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and examined, were the Doctors; and the very Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph it ſelf. It may be juſtly preſumed that he not intending it for the Preſs, but for the private uſe of ſome private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; he took not ſo much care in the Compoſure of it, as he would have done, had he deſigned it to the adventure of a publick Teſt. O Sir, how would you take it, to have any of your indigeſted Scripts, never intended (at leaſt in that dreſs) for a publick view, and what concerned points greatly, and with too much animoſity controverted, to be ſo expoſed under your name, and dealt with ſo Critically, and with ſo much reflection? I have known you very tender in printing what was of great uſe, and not lyable to much oppoſition; without ſome plain intimation of the Authors conſent; as in the caſe of Judge <hi>Hale</hi> of worthy Memory. And I take it to be a right in works of this nature, that the Author be owner, and diſpoſer of them as his property; till he have made them common, and without limitation; as any other work whatſoever. But Sir, to conclude this unpleaſant Section, I never knew a precedent of the like nature, and it may be nor your ſelf neither.</p>
            <p>I ſhall in the next place look into the reaſons you give, for thus expoſing the Arguments; notwithſtanding the grief and reluctancy you profeſs at ſuch an undertaking, againſt ſo holy, and worthy a Perſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Becauſe,</hi> (to give your own words,) <hi>The laſt ſheet of my reaſons for Communion being Printed, and the oppoſite</hi> 12 <hi>Arguments ſuddenly ſent me, as being in many hands, and ſuch as would fruſtrate all that I had written, if they were not anſwered: For the ſake of ſuch as have not skill to ſee Truth from Errour, and are led by prejudice, and names, I durſt not in Conſcience let them paſs unanſwered; they being of ſuch dangerous tendency, and ſo exceeding erroneous and fallacious.</hi> Poſtiſcript. pag. 1.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that as to your mention of the <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> being <hi>ſuddenly</hi> ſent you; I know not well what to make of it for your juſtification. For, it appears by this, that you had not the notice of theſe Arguments fathered on the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106428:5"/>Doctor, or at leaſt not the arguments themſelves, and their tendency; but after the Printing of the laſt ſheet of the tracts, bound up together with this: And then your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking cannot be excuſed from too great ſuddenneſs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitancy. Moreover it is a fair ground of doubting, that they were not in many hands; ſeeing they came to your hands, and (for ought I know, or you ſay) to your notice no ſooner: And I know that I have ſeen a Copy of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like them about a twelve month ſince, and I believe were but in few hands before your concerning your ſelf with them.</p>
            <p>But as to that part of the information which looks like the prevailing motive, that <hi>they were ſuch as would fruſtrate all you had written, if they were not anſwered.</hi> Either you believed it, or not: If you did not credit it, it would have proved but <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> and wrought no farther effects by you. But if you did believe it, I know not who can excuſe your ſo eaſy credulity of that, which was not only improbable, but as near as can well be imagined to impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Improbable (if you have given a right, and due Character of the Arguments) to work any ſuch great effects againſt <hi>your Arguments,</hi> which you do not ſeem to ſuſpect of any feeble parts, at leaſt ſuch as may indanger their main Cauſe, by whatever force aſſaulted. I muſt here neceſſarily tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe your Character of the 12 Arguments, you take Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> to task for.</p>
            <p>In your Preface, toward the end, <hi>It's true that aboundance of good people fear, and diſtaſt Communion in the Lyturgy: What wonder, when ſuch reaſonings as theſe</hi> 12 <hi>Arguments (which how groſs ſoever, people have not the skill to anſwer) perſuade them it is falſe Worſhip, and heinous ſin.</hi> Dear Sir, I fear that thoſe people, who have not the skill to anſwer the 12 Arguments; will be found to want skill enough to diſcover the ſtrength of yours. And I confeſs 'tis matter of lamentation, that on all ſides Peoples Opinions are moſtly, and moſt ſtrongly (I will not ſay guided, but) maſtered by their affections: and 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all our power to cure the diſorder, though the beſt way I know, is ſo far to lay aſide all the very appearances of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and bitterneſs; and to be clothed with ſo much love,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106428:6"/>meekneſs, and all that's lovely, that we may win their hearts, and then it will not be hard to influence their heads, <hi>Ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum recipientis recipiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I have not ſaid the worſt you ſay of the 12 Arguments in contempt. You add Poſtſcript p. 6. <hi>The</hi> 12 <hi>Arguments I underſtand are likeſt to prevail moſt, by the honour of Dr.</hi> Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens <hi>name; more then by any ſtrength that is in them: I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as long as I could, to believe that they were not his, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as frivolous, and fallacious as any of the reſt, and one Error managed with above fourty miſtakes.</hi> Here Sir you render them very feeble things, but for Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> name; and yet you have contributed the ſtrength of Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> name to them in Print; which you had far better have left out, upon more ſcores than one. But how long were you willing to believe they were not his? Not long to be ſure; for it was a very little while betwixt your receipt of the Arguments, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, and intitling Dr. <hi>O.</hi> to them. How frivolous the Arguments are in your account, may be beſt underſtood by the Compariſon, <hi>as frivolous as any of the reſt.</hi> Among the reſt were Mr. <hi>Warners,</hi> of which, you ſay in the next words foregoing. <hi>Mr.</hi> Warner <hi>hath ſince Printed a farther Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the ſame charge of Idolatry, and falſe worſhip; againſt the manner of Worſhip not inſtituted,—and ſaid ſo little, that I will not write for him that cannot himſelf confute him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort Sir, I know not Mr. <hi>Warner,</hi> nor his writings; but thoſe you ſpeak of, are ſo feeble, that he who cannot confute them himſelf, ſhall have no help from you; which in ſenſe is, they are ſo eaſily confuted, that he that hath any degree of underſtanding, or that is capable of information, may confute Mr. <hi>Warners</hi> Arguments, if he will; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Doctors, being never a jot more invincible, if you can but get over his name. O for Moderation! This over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing paſſionate work ſpoils all. Well Sir, I ſuppoſe you will allow me that the 12 Arguments conſidered nakedly, were not the danger you feared.</p>
            <p>Yet I muſt not forget that I ſaid it was next impoſſible (take them as armed as you can make, or imagine them) that they ſhould do ſuch miſchief as your informer affected you with the apprehenſions of, <hi>viz. To fruſtrate all that you had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106428:6"/>written:</hi> We will ſuppoſe it meant of all the tracts bound up with this. Dear Sir, could you imagine that thoſe Scripts would viſit as many hands as your Prints, or that all that had your Prints, and might receive any good by them, would certainly meet with theſe 12 Arguments, and be conquered by them. I beſeech you Sir, be not ſo eaſily perſuaded by ſuch hot-headed heedleſs reporters, as to make their reports, that carry precipitancy, weakneſs, and contradiction in their Fore-heads, the occaſions of ſuch diſtaſtful (and J fear worſe) tasks as this.</p>
            <p>The other motive to expoſe them is, the Doctors name being ſo prevalent. But I pray Sir, who gave them that name? Truly ſome few private Perſons privately; but Mr. <hi>B.</hi> upon the publick Theatre, with a <hi>Noverint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi.</hi> But Sir, you Printed them with the Antidote, both to the thing the Poyſon, and the Vehicle, the Doctors name, that did ſo powerfully inſinuate it. But Sir, what is this, but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing your name to the Doctors? Your name thruſt in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily (ſome ſay violently) to his, drag'd upon the Stage after his Deceaſe, againſt his will? Seriouſly Sir, though I have heard many of your Friends, who would rather be partial for you, than unjuſt, ſpeak of this matter; I never heard one of them attempt an excuſe for your concerning Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> name in your Print. And ſome will not ſtick to ſay (do you or I what we can to the contrary) that this is but the working of an old Spleen againſt the Doctor, and taking very ungentily this advantage. But Sir, I am confident whatever the deceitfulneſs of ſin may do, you would abhor the appearance of ſuch an evil.</p>
            <p>I have not overlookt what you have ſaid, as well to juſtify your ſelf from all prejudice againſt, or deſigns upon the Doctors name; as alſo that you have ſaid to render it a ſtrength to Weakneſs, and Errour; and a prejudice againſt Truth, and Argument. And indeed in many things you ſpeak very honourably of him. But Reverend Sir, whereas you ſay, <hi>It is ſo far from your deſign, to wrong the name of Doctor</hi> Owen <hi>by this defence;</hi> If you have done, or it be the tendency of your work to do it, though the deſign be far from it, that will not be a juſt compenſation.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106428:7"/>
            <p> Now Sir, I remember where you your ſelf have hinted an excellent advantage to have avoided, much of what is now ſo diſtaſted. You ſay in your Letter to the unknown Author, <hi>That the Doctor owned the ill Principle, which you now confute,</hi> viz. <hi>againſt all Publick Worſhip by Liturgy, and againſt mans power to command any more than Chriſt hath done in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and manner of Worſhip, and Church Government;</hi> and this to be ſeen in his Preface to his Original of Churches, his vindication of the Nonconformiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And you add alſo, <hi>That for the many healing, peaceable paſſages in thoſe Books you long purpoſely forbore all contradiction of him in it, (though you plainly anſwered his Arguments in your</hi> Cure of Church Diviſions.</p>
            <p>When I look on the uſe you make of theſe paſſages, I am confirmed how different mens Conſtructions may be; and how cautious we ought to be of partiality. Sir, I find the improvement you make of the ſame ill principle in his Books (as you call it) is to countenance your opinion, that theſe 12 Arguments have the ſame father. But Sir, you know that as <hi>many men, many minds,</hi> ſo many men in ſome one Opinion (and that none of the beſt) may be of one mind: ſo that this concludes not they were the Doctors. Yet there were no great hurt in all this; but that you anſwered his Arguments, in your <hi>Cure of Church Diviſions,</hi> is news to me; wherein I can find neither his name, nor Arguments, nor the names of the Books you ſay they were in, to any ſuch purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It appears by what you ſay, that the Doctor had in Print aſſerted the ſame Principles contained in his 12 Arguments; and not only at looſe, but, <hi>ex animo &amp; induſtria.</hi> What a brave advantage had you here, to have incountred the ſame ill Principles under the Doctors avowed name, all in a poſture, wherein the Doctor had Harnaſſed, and Marſhalled them for the open Field? Who would have ſaid this had been ſurreptitious, or ungentile? or not warrantable by the ſtricteſt Rules of Eccleſiaſtical Combating.</p>
            <p>Whereas, as the caſe ſtands, we ſhall not hear ſo well of it, nor will it bear it.</p>
            <p>I have done Sir, with what I thought amiſs (at leaſt I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106428:7"/>though fit to write) in the grounds of your writing againſt the 12 Arguments, and confuting them as Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi> The next things I propoſed to conſider, was, What manner of Treatment the Doctor hath from you in your ſcrutiny into thoſe 12 Arguments as his.</p>
            <p>It is not only obſervable, but greatly obſerved, that in all this tract, you ſpeak in the ſecond Perſon to a dead man, which is ſuch a ſoleciſm, or riddle, that I meet not with any that can reconcile to your Learning, or Candor. If it ſhould be ſaid that all this while you forgot your Grammar, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected it: That is not to be admitted: and if you did it upon deſign, I would you had explained your ſelf, and ſaved me that neceſſary, but thankleſs Office. Should I ſay, you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps had no deſign in it at all, but did it from firſt to laſt, <hi>ex improviſo:</hi> This would reflect too much upon your Prudence, and Care: But the ſenſe of it muſt be had (people are ſo concerned at it) though it be at the charge of a diver of <hi>Delos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are only two conſtructions that I can obtain a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, the firſt <hi>leſs,</hi> the other <hi>more</hi> probable. The firſt, that it <hi>may</hi> reſemble thoſe Poetical Raptures, wherein Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are carried by the exceſs of ſome paſſion, to feign to themſelves that the dead are living, and the abſent preſent, to whom, as ſuch, they direct their ſpeeches, with a greater, or more grateful ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The latter, and more probable ſenſe I take from a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of this manner of application to the deal (as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>to</hi> them, as well as <hi>of</hi> them) with a very remarkable paſſage of your own, and much talked of by underſtanding perſons. It is in your <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> p. 7. in theſe words, <hi>I doubt not, but his Soul</hi> [Dr. <hi>Owens,</hi>] <hi>is now with Chriſt: and that, though Heaven have no ſorrow, it hath great repentance and that Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>is now more againſt the receiving of this miſtake then I am: and by defending it, you far more diſpleaſe him, than me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Worthy Sir, that you here affirm without doubting, (for your <hi>I doubt not</hi> in the beginning, qualifies all you ſay, to the end of what I have tranſcribed) that Heaven hath great <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and that the Dr. <hi>there</hi> is more <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106428:8"/>of his Opinion, which you call a miſtake, than you your ſelf: And that muſt be a diſpleaſure of no ſmall degree, if we meaſure it by your expreſſions of your own, at the defence of the ſaid miſtake. What ſoundneſs there is in the Opinion, that there is repentance, and diſpleaſure to the Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as a foreſaid, ſhall be conſidered by and by. But if it be your Opinion, that Dr.<hi>O.</hi> will be ſo greatly diſpleaſed now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, at defending the ſaid miſtake by any on Earth; it muſt needs be your Opinion, that he will know if any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be made. And if his knowledge now in Heaven be ſo extenſive, I, and all men that underſtand ſenſe, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, you did not ſo impertinently addreſs your writing to <hi>him</hi> after he was <hi>dead:</hi> Only we yet underſtand not, when you expect an Anſwer from him, or <hi>how;</hi> except we muſt take that ſpeech you have made for him, in your Poſtſcript, to be <hi>re vera,</hi> the Doctors, and then you may have an Anſwer when &amp; what you will. I know not Sir, whether you will tak<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this as jeſt, or earneſt, or both: I am ſatisfied it well ſuits to the Refolution of the Queſtion, and the occaſion by you gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. What is next to follow, I am ſure requires weighing, and is no jeſting matter.</p>
            <p>Your repreſenting Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in Heaven, ſo highly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at thoſe who defend on the Earth his ſaid miſtake, hath two great Contradictions in it, to the generally received Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all that I have met with, as to one of them; and all Proteſtants as to the other. Yet you ſay, you do not ſo much as <hi>doubt</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Is Heaven a place and ſtate of perfect reſt and peace, joy, delight and pleaſures, without the leaſt mixture of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries? Where <hi>God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying; neither ſhall there be any more pain,</hi> Rev. 21.4. And have you now brought it to this, that the Saints in Heaven may be affected with great diſpleaſure? I know you do not make Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s eſtate in Heaven, an exception to the general Rule, ſo much to his diſadvantage. And if ſuch as he, or your ſelf, when ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at that Bleſſed State, are yet liable to ſo much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, what an allay of their happineſs may <hi>they</hi> expect in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who in compariſon of ſuch Stars, near to the firſt degree
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106428:8"/>of magnitude, are hudled among the unobſerved <hi>Sporades?</hi> Dear Sir, I ſhould have been glad to have found moſt of this paſſage in your Errata of the Printer, or Copy. I doubt not but the good Doctor in Heaven, for all his miſtakes on Earth, hath feelingly and experimentally corrected this uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table miſtake of yours, that renders the Saints everlaſting reſt not ſuch a reſt, nor ſo deſirable as you more truly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it in your <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt, part</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>This Reſt containeth a perfect freedom from all the evils that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied us through our courſe—And doubtleſs there is not ſuch a thing as grief and ſorrow known there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would fain have perſuaded my ſelf by ſome diſtinction, to put a better, and more pleaſant countenance upon the word <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> and agreeable to the heavenly Reſt, but it was beyond my <hi>Talent:</hi> I would have reconciled its ſenſe to <hi>mere</hi> diſlike, or diſapprobation; acts of the underſtanding and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may be exerted without grief, but diſpleaſure I found would ſtill remain, not only <hi>(in tantum)</hi> a privation of, but a contradiction to pleaſure, as far as <hi>diſhoneſty</hi> is to honeſty, or <hi>diſeaſe</hi> to eaſe. O how uneaſie would the Saints in Heaven be, if they were liable to diſpleaſure, at the pleaſure of any on Earth, who ſhall well meaningly, or maliciouſly, defend their, or others Errours!</p>
            <p>But I muſt not paſs by the ſecond moſt obvious ſenſe of your words, which is, that the Saints in Heaven know what is done, written, or ſaid in this world, after their deceaſe. How can Dr. <hi>O.</hi> be diſpleaſed at that he hath no notice of? How will you be able to prove that he ſhall have notice of any ones defending the miſtake you ſpeak of. I am not ſure that the Angels do not give notice of many things done on Earth, to the Saints in Heaven. Our Saviour tells us, That <hi>there is joy in Heaven, and in the preſence of the Angels, over one ſinner that is converted,</hi> Luke 15. And it is very congruous to the ſtate of the Bleſſed, to have motives of joy imparted to them. But it is dangerous to be wiſe in theſe matters, above what is written.</p>
            <p>You know Sir, what work the Papiſts make of praying to deceaſed Saints, either to do for them what they pray for, or to intercede for them at leaſt. And that this is charged
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106428:9"/>on them by the Proteſtants, as Idolatry, or Superſtition, or both. Now Sir, if they could gain but this point, that it is <hi>undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly</hi> true, that the Saints in Heaven know what we on Earth ſay, or do, they would diſarm us of our beſt weapon againſt that piece of Superſtition, which is, that we have no aſſurance that the Saints we pray to, hear or know what, or when we pray; and therefore whatever their power or intereſt in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may be, it would be abſurd, and fruitleſs, and bear no parity of reaſon with our deſiring the Saints on Earth to pray for us; for which we have a precept, and an aſſurance that we can acquaint them with our deſires.</p>
            <p>I know not Sir, what your abilities may produce in the defence and juſtification of ſuch expreſſions: But, for my ſelf and ſuch pore-blind creatures as I: We dare not make ſuch dangerous leaps.</p>
            <p>What you ſay of Repentance, <hi>viz. That though Heaven hath no ſorrow, it hath great repentance,</hi> is not ſo ſafe, and clear as to be ſwallowed without chewing: and is to me a very ſolitary notion, and it may be to moſt others that are no ſtrangers to reading. The Greek words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; whatever ſignifications their etymologies, or their uſe in prophane Authors may afford, which are indeed very many, and various: we muſt ſtick to their ſenſe in Scripture, when we put men upon the duty, and uſe the Engliſh word Repentance in that ſenſe, or thoſe ſenſes it obtains amongſt Engliſh Men, (when we uſe it in a general notion) who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their own language.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you that the more general, if not the only ſenſes of the words in <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> New Teſtament, are in the Latin <hi>Poenitet, Poenitentia moveor, poenitentiam ago, &amp; reſipiſco,</hi> from whence are the Nouns <hi>poenitentia,</hi> and <hi>reſipiſcentia;</hi> which anſwer to our two Engliſh words, Compunction, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or Converſion, both in judgment, affection, and practice. But our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word, <hi>Repentance</hi> takes in both, and (when it reſpects men) ſounds very lamely, and defectively without grief, or ſorrow. And (not to ſpeak of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in an Evangelical ſenſe, or Repentance to eternal life, which, though it be conditional of, and preparatory to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, cannot in all the eſſential, and integral parts of it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106428:9"/>be congruous to the ſtate of the bleſſed in Heaven) Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the common notion, and ſenſe, in which we muſt take it here, is often underſtood of ſorrow, and vexation, without any change of practice, or <hi>after</hi> Wiſdom; but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if ever of after Wiſdom, or change of practice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſorrow, or vexation. And therefore, however you may come-off (at leaſt in appearance) by ſheltring in the ſenſe of forreign words, ſome part of the true evangelical notion of it; it doth, and will ſound very offenſively, and moſt by far, will either not underſtand you, or miſunderſtand you.</p>
            <p>If I may venture Sir, to ſhoot my bolt, to hit your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I ſhall take it to be that, according to the Greek words, they ſhall in Heaven be after-wiſe, or a Saint in Heaven ſhall <hi>mutare mentem in melius,</hi> have a better underſtanding than he had here; and diſapprove what he here thought well, and true: it might as eaſily have been ſo expreſſed, (if this were all you intended) and have ſaved many a puzling thought, and untoward cenſure.</p>
            <p>Another thing, Sir, in your manage of this work, that gives great diſtaſt, and I cannot contradict their cenſure, who ſay that it looks with a very unkind aſpect (to ſay no worſe) on the Doctor is, that throughout your examination of the Arguments (except the laſt) which you ſo <hi>poſitively,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly</hi> intitle the Doctor to: When you conclude you have found a <hi>miſtake,</hi> you mark it in a numerical order in the Margin, <hi>viz.</hi> The I. Errour, the II. the III. Errour, and ſo on, till you arrive at laſt to the XLII. Errour: ſo that if your Reader ſhould forget a great part of your ſuppoſed Errours, found out by you in the Arguments; he may be inabled to retain this black Character of the Doctor, that he was ſuch an erroneous Perſon, that he was a man of forty two Errours in ſo ſmall a tract, as might well be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in half a ſheet of Paper. From whence an unfriendly prejudiced Reader will conclude that his Errours in all his large, and manifold writings were <hi>tantum non</hi> innumerable. But though you were ſo ſevere, you were not leſs merciful than the Jews; for you bated him thoſe ſtripes, you might by the ſame Law have impoſed on the laſt Argument alſo. Sir, this is not the common method of Theological Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106428:10"/>it muſt have ſome more peculiar impulſe to derive from; whether good, or bad, I leave to the diſcretion of others, but chiefly to your own; who ſhould know, beyond any Mortal, the temper, and agitations of your own Spirit: But I am not dainty to affirm, that if others examining your Writings, ſhould take this liberty to mark out all that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>their</hi> Sentiments, it would riſe to a long ſum; and as it would be very indecent in them, it would not be a little diſtaſtful to your ſelf: <hi>If ye fulfil the Royal Law according to the Scripture; Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, ye do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay in your Preface, line II. <hi>Some wiſe, and good men will blame me for making our differences to be ſo much known:</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>for remembring old miſcarriages: I obey my Conſcience: All theſse things are</hi> commonly <hi>known already, and we hear ſharply of them from God, and Man, becauſe Men hear not our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but our Juſtification: Had we confeſſed, God is faithful to forgive, Impenitence threatens our yet greater ſuffering.</hi> And truly Sir, I take this expoſing old miſcarriages ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with ſuch aſperity, and extremity, to be ſo liable to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that renders your Controverſies with thoſe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in them, both diſtaſtful, and fruitleſs: Nor doth it hear well from ſtanders by, of any calmneſs, or moderation.</p>
            <p>Reverend, and worthy Sir, I beg your Candor, Patience, and Pardon, for I may need them all (though I ſhall give as little occaſion as I can, or the thing will bear for their Trial) if I impartially weigh your own Objection, and your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned Defence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some wiſe and good men will blame you for,</hi> &amp;c. This you had a proſpect of, either from the nature of the thing, as meriting it, or that good, and wiſe men will miſtake, and be injurious; or from what you have had experience of, upon the like, or far leſs occaſion. I will not entertain a thought of the firſt, for that were to charge you with a ſin againſt your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and not only the ſin of Preſumption (which ſome natures powerfully and inſenſibly incline to,) but alſo a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſin. I ſhould greatly wrong you, if I ſhould be ſo uncharitable. I heartily believe that the great Wheel that moves you is, a Zeal for God. But I think both the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might perſuade you to expect the blame you ſeak of.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106428:10"/>
            <p> Now Sir, ſhould you not well have conſidered this, &amp; taken more time to do it calmly, &amp; coolly than you did; ſeeing you knew <hi>wiſe &amp; good men</hi> would think it blame-worthy. Theſe were not raſh, headleſs, heedleſs, proud ignorants; but <hi>good</hi> men, and therefore <hi>well meaning;</hi> and <hi>wiſe</hi> men, and therefore had skill to <hi>ſay,</hi> as well, as <hi>mean</hi> well. <hi>There is that ſpeaketh like the piercings of a</hi> Sword, <hi>but the Tongue of the Wiſe is health.</hi> It may be you will ſay that you did alſo expect that ſome good, and wiſe men would <hi>commend,</hi> or ſpeak well of you for it; and ſo there would be ſome againſt ſome. Dear Sir, believe me, that I ſpeak impartial truth: I have known many wiſe, and good men blame, and not one commend it; no, not of thoſe that in the points here controverted, are of your own Opinion, and Practice. What do you think of the healing Parliament, that provided by a Act of <hi>Oblivion</hi> againſt ſuch remembrances? There was the Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and the Authority of the whole Nation; Head, and Members a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. Did your Judgment conſult this before you wrote it; or do you think it is <hi>eximious</hi> Chriſtianity, to act the part of <hi>Hyaena</hi>'s; to feed on dead Carkaſes, when they have torn them out of their Graves? Or were the wiſe, and good men the far greater number, that were for thus <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring old miſcarriages?</hi> How came you by the <hi>Poll</hi> to make ſuch a concluſion? I think the Parliament <hi>(in this Caſe)</hi> might be ſo dead a weight, that all others could not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance. Truly Sir, all theſe Conſiderations, without other Auxiliaries, ſhould at leaſt have ſtayed your hand for altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this matter, if not condemned the firſt motion.</p>
            <p>In the next place it is fit that I give ſome account of what old miſcarriages you are pleaſed to expoſe by way of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and place to the account of Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> Party, but eſpecially of himſelf, as the Maſter ſeparate. You fill up more than three pages, with one intire harangue of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>viz.</hi> from p. 25. to p. 29. <hi>incluſivè.</hi> And you begin with what you ſay you will <hi>paſs by,</hi> ſcil. <hi>The Hiſtories of</hi> Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>and</hi> Muncer; <hi>and of</hi> David George <hi>in</hi> Holland, <hi>and of</hi> Henry Nichols, <hi>and the Familiſts, which were the</hi> Off-ſpring <hi>of</hi> Separation: <hi>And the ſad conflicts which they had againſt the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Nonconformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106428:11"/>
            <p> Your buſineſs is to make all the extravagancies the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Perſons acted, and fomented, the Fruits of Separation, (as you tell us elſewhere) or elſe you produce them very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently. But I beſecch you Sir, doth it follow that being Conſequents, they were Effects? Have there not been as great Diſsorders, and Confuſions of Civil Government, where there was no Separation from Liturgies, and great Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Rebellions too; which if they had had ſucceſs, might have arrived at as great Diſaſters, and Confuſions as any other? You go on, and give a <hi>ſubſtratum</hi> of moſt of the miſeries, and miſchiefs, diſorders, and extravagancies in Church and State, Spiritual, and Civil concerns here in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> from the year 40. to 59. And I am of the opinion Sir, that as neceſſary as you make theſe remembrances to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felling the Arguments againſt Lyturgical Worſhip; If you cannot overthrow it without theſe inſtances, you cannot do it by them. For, whereas the Argument lies againſt the Lyturgy, not only from the Conſequences, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary effects of Lyturgies; (I will not ſay with what ſtrength) your inſtances reach the Conſequences, but not the neceſſary effects of breaking that boundary. It muſt be confeſſed that if men had kept to the Lyturgy, and its prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts; they had not then ſeparated from the Church, or the Churches worſhipping in that form: And it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that thoſe who brake thoſe bounds, were not neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to run <hi>mad,</hi> nor forſake <hi>Parochial</hi> publick worſhip: Elſe, how came it to paſs, that when the Lyturgy itſelf as thrown out, the Pariſh Churches, notwithſtanding, were as much frequented as ever they were, ſince <hi>England</hi> was a Nation; (and with as honourable as Miniſtry) and of thoſe the far greater number, were not much offended at the Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies expulſion? And thoſe who took ſuch extravagant leaps, <hi>might</hi> have ſtopt there, as well as others. But as to Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in State, we need not look beyond-ſea for like inſtances: The Commons Inſurrections, the Baros Wars in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of the Houſes of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> the horrid Tyranny, and Cruelties of <hi>Richard</hi> 3. will afford enough of Extravagancies, many <hi>acted,</hi> more <hi>intended,</hi> and no Religion concerned in the caſe. Yea, in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Edw. 6th</hi> time, were very great Commotions, and Conteſts for the intereſt of a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106428:11"/>Popiſh, or Proteſtant Lyturgy, which King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8th wittly called the old <hi>mumpſimus,</hi> and the new <hi>ſumpſimus.</hi> And Sir, I have ſeldom ſeen ſtrength, or calmneſs, or ſucceſs in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Controverſies, and forcing Arguments from pretended Iſſues, or Conſequences, <hi>good,</hi> or <hi>had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, Let us hear your defence, and it is this, <hi>I obey my Conſcience.</hi> You know Sir what might be ſaid, and what has been ſaid of the woful iſſues of <hi>obeying Conſcience:</hi> This may ſatisfy our ſelves, it is not enough to ſatisfy others. Yet Sir, you believe, and I too, that men muſt not caſt off obedience to Conſcience, and condemn obedience to it, becauſe of the wretched effects of ſome mens Conſciences, which are not to be imputed <hi>ſimply</hi> to their Obedeince, to their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, but to ſome ill circumſtances, under which their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are, and which ought to be conſcientiouſly, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially examined, and corrected.</p>
            <p>But you add ſomewhat for reaſons, to ſatisfy your Readers Conſcience, as well as your own, <hi>ſcil. All theſe things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known already.</hi> Pardon me, Sir, if I believe, and <hi>ſay</hi> this is a miſtake: your <hi>all</hi> is ſomewhat too many for this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation. Was it commonly known before you made it ſo (ſuppoſing the Manuſcript to be the Doctors) that Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> ever ſaid, as you affirm he doth in the following words? <hi>That Gods Worſhip hath no Accidentals, that all that is in it, and belonging to it, and the manner of it, is falſe Worſhip; it it have not a Divine Inſtitution in particular; that all Lyturgies (as ſuch) are ſuch falſe Worſhip</hi> (and not the <hi>Engliſh</hi> only) <hi>uſed to defeat Chriſts promiſed gifts, and Gods Spirit. And this</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is the cauſe you write againſt, and bid your Reader under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, or meddle not with what he underſtands not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, the matter of Fact before us is to be conſidered. You begin your report thus: 1. <hi>That Gods Worſhip,</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Owen) hath no Accidentals,</hi> and ſo proceed in a different letter, as I have tranſcribed it. Sir, you are not ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with writing, as not to know that paſſages affirmed to be an Authors, in a different letter, ought to be exactly, and preciſely the Authors, without adding, taking away, or tranſpoſing a word, ſyllable, or letter that is material, eſpecially when oppoſed. But that you have done ſo here, I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106428:12"/>cannot find, after ſix times moſt diligently peruſing all the Arguments according to <hi>your</hi> Edition, meerly for the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the laſt paſſages. You ſet out with numb. 1. which is no ſenſe, without a ſecond; yet where you began, you made an end of numbring here; though you did not ſo of the Doctors Errors. I mention this, chiefly to ſhew how heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful you were when you wrote this paſſage. And let this go for the firſt note, which ſhall have this as a ſecond, that you point not your Reader to the number of the pages in your book (which you might have done, it being in your Poſtſcript) wherein theſe paſſages were, or any one of them, nor tell me in which of the Arguments they are to be found. This hath put me to more trouble to write a few lines as I ought, than ſome would take under the like difficulties to write ſo many pages. And I do affirm, that there being three, and but three compleat ſentences in all; there is not one of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, nor in that order in any of the 12 Arguments. What may be implied, or the genuine ſenſe of what is ſaid in the Arguments, I do not here concern my ſelf with. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I ought not to be charged with <hi>ſaying</hi> any thing but what I have ſaid <hi>expreſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſentence or Propoſition is ſhort, and ſomewhat I find like it in p. 13. thus: <hi>It is replyed, there is nothing Acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in the Worſhip of God.</hi> You report it, <hi>Gods Worſhip hath no Accidentals.</hi> And I ſuppoſe, (waving the term <hi>Acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> as to its fitneſs in this place) that <hi>having</hi> no Accidentals, and no Accidentals <hi>in</hi> the Worſhip of God, are of very different Conſtruction; being <hi>in</hi> it, making at leaſt an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral part; <hi>having</hi> may take in variable circumſtances of time, place, indifferent poſtures, and the like; ſome, or other of which are neceſſary to it as an action <hi>in genere naturali.</hi> And the Author, (whoſoever he be) explains his ſenſe of <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentals,</hi> within 2 or three lines thus; <hi>But all things</hi> duely <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it, are parts of it; or of its ſubſiſtence: outward cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are natural, and occaſional, no Accidental parts of Worſhip.</hi> And p. 16. of your Edition (for I have no other.) <hi>Outward Rites, and Modes of Worſhip Divinely Inſtituted, and determined, do become the neceſſary parts of Divine Worſhip. Therefore ſuch as are Humanly Inſtituted, appointed, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106428:12"/>are thereby made parts of Worſhip: namely, that which is falſe, for want of Divine Inſtitution.</hi> I doubt not but Dr. <hi>O.</hi> was able to ſind apt terms to expreſs his ſenſe by. But the Authors meaning by what I have ſaid, is but this. All things of Divine appointment are neceſſary, <hi>neceſſitate praecepti</hi> to the Worſhip for which they are ſo appointed: and therefore eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry human invention, made <hi>neceſſary</hi> to any part of Divine Worſhip, is falſe Worſhip; becauſe it is put into the room of a Divine Inſtitution, which it hath not. Whether it be a good Argument, or not, I do not determine; but that this is the Authors ſenſe, is plain, and ſo taken, is not ſo bad, or abſurd as you make it ſeem to be. Now Sir, the aboveſaid differences betwixt you and others, and the Doctor, were not <hi>all</hi> ſo commonly known already, and it may be were not in being, and ſo not poſſible to be known.</p>
            <p>But for matters of Fact which you expoſe, and charge par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, or by name upon the Doctor, I ſhall give two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. You ſay, p. 27. <hi>After the death of</hi> Oliver, <hi>his Son ſet up, and his Parliament firſt pull'd down (in which the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Author now oppoſed, told me he was an Agent) and next himſelf.</hi> And p. 29. <hi>But I will tell the Biſhops, that they ſhould not be too angry with the learned Author of theſe</hi> 12 <hi>Arguments; for I know not three men alive, whom they are more beholden to for their reſtitution, by opening the door, and ſweeping the way, and melting down, or pulverizing all that was likely to have reſiſted them.</hi> Thus far it is intelligible: But I am directed in the Errata to add immediately, <hi>than thoſe of the Opinion he pleads for,</hi> (and now let him underſtand it that can) <hi>I ſpeak not of the intention, but the action.</hi> I think you have rendred him here ſuch a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, miſchievous buſy-body, as neither the Biſhops conſidering the action without the intention; nor many others conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring both, or which you will, have any great reaſon to thank him: nor his Friends to thank you for theſe Characters. Yet you afford us one more that outgoes all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What they truly upbraid us with in malice, let us openly lament in ſerious penitence, and not ſtand to a ſinful, dividing Principle, and Cauſe; leſt the</hi> Saints be blamed, <hi>that have fathered it on God. This learned Author hath done otherwiſe himſelf, and ſo hath the Party now oppoſed. He and I knew the man, who was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106428:13"/>Paſtor to the Commanders of the Army, when they pull'd down, and ſet up, and again pull'd down, till they had turned their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Bulwarks into Atoms: And when he ſaw what they had done, ſaid,</hi> [I wonder the People do not caſt ſtones at us as we go along the Streets] <hi>was not this a blaming of his Flock? He knew how oft the addreſſes of the Separatiſts to the ſeveral ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly erected Soveraignties did change their minds, and cry</hi> pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus <hi>by their new Addreſſes for the old. And why may not we blame them that blamed themſelves, for fathering their miſtakes on God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall a little comment on this Text, which would better have become the Obſervator, than Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who will ſay as much for him, and thoſe he calls Innocents: and Crucify all alike, as under one Condemnation. And ſurely ſome of theſe things were ſo far from being commonly known, that they muſt ſtand on your <hi>only</hi> legs for their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, or none at all that I know of. You blame them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they blame not themſelves for theſe things, and yet tell the world they have blamed themſelves, and how you can equal their worſt Adverſaries in a ſcornful, virulent, ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on their faces.</p>
            <p>Worthy Sir, I pray bear with a truth, which I hope your piety will make ſome good uſe of (though it muſt be now in the after-part) I know not any man alive, who was leſs fit to throw theſe, or any other reſlections on the Doctor; I ſpeak it not in reſpect of your Abilities, which I value, and honour; but in reſpect of the want of that good underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you, while the Dr. lived; which was commonly noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: I ſay not where the fault lay, I ſhould have been glad to have been a means to cure, or conceal it.</p>
            <p>But take things as they are, and it will be next a Miracle, if this work of yours be not imputed to ſome ill Original; and then 'tis like to do little of that good you really intend by it. And I think you did not well weigh thoſe words, p. 2. of your Preface, when you wrote them, <hi>ſoil. And the</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>that I deal with, neceſſitateth me to recite the late fruits of Separation,</hi> &amp;c. Dear Sir, do you not tell the world here, <hi>who,</hi> and what you had in your Eye. You ſay not here, the <hi>matter</hi> of the Arguments put you on ſuch a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106428:13"/>but <hi>the Author you deal with.</hi> The Author, whom you will have to be no other than the late Reverend, Learned, and Pious Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi> No doubt but Arguments, be they what they will, muſt have an Author. But if they had been aſcribed to ſome other Author (as your words import) there had been no ſuch neceſſity on you <hi>to recite the late fruits of Separation,</hi> and what follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some of the pretended Errours conſidered, as they are fixed in a Numerical Order, and aſcribed to D.O.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THis is a Task, Sir, that muſt be done with great Caution, not only with regard to your Anſwers, or your Perſon; but the ſubject: which puts the hilt in the hand of him that writes in its Countenance, but the point to him, who ſhall be ſo daring as to offend againſt it. But I hope I ſhall do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lyable to exception; for I ſhall not undertake any thing againſt the Lyturgy, or Communion thereby: only, fairly conſider how far you have juſtly fixed thoſe Errours, on the Author of the Arguments, which you call Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, I ſhall not take it for granted that your Edition in Print is exactly a true Copy of the Autograph, nor will, or can you your ſelf aſſirm with any ground how far it is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſed, by that time it arrived to your hands; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall think it reaſonable to put the beſt conſtructions that equity will allow on the diſadvantaged ſide. Only I muſt tell my Reader my Order, that he may know which is which.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Arguments words are in the common letter with theſe notes, ["] at the left hand of the line, Mr. <hi>Baxters,</hi> in a different letter, and mine in the common letter, except now and then a ſpecial word.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Poſition.</hi> It is not lawful for us to go to, and joyn in publick Worſhip by the Common-Prayer; becauſe that Worſhip itſelf, according to the rule of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, is not lawful.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106428:14"/>
            <p> You anſwer, 1. <hi>I ſhall uſe the ſame method that he hath uſed, and firſt give you my Poſitions, and then the ſuppoſed matter of fact; and then conſider his Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poſit. <hi>It is not only lawful, but a duty for thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have better publick Worſhip, without more hurt than benefit; and are near a competent Pariſh Miniſter to go to, and joyn in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, performed according to the Lyturgy, and in Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Communion: And for thoſe that can have better, to joyn ſometimes with ſuch Pariſh Churches, when their forbearance ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly ſeemeth to ſignify that they take ſuch communion for unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and would ſo tempt others to the ſame accuſation, and unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Separation. The Hiſtory of the matter of Fact muſt be premiſed, for the right deciding of the cauſe, which is as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt ſay ſomewhat of the Authors Poſition, and then of yours. The Authors Poſition (as you Print it) conſiſts of a Poſition, and alſo the reaſon or ground of it. And I find the reaſon exceeding the limits of what was to be proved: which makes it look not like Dr. <hi>Owens.</hi> But to take it as it is, the Poſition if [it is not lawful for <hi>us</hi> to go and joyn in publick Worſhip by <hi>the</hi> Common-Prayer.] He doth not ſay it is unlawful for <hi>any,</hi> and for ought you know, this <hi>us</hi> whom he concerned in it, might be a very few, to whom this Manuſcript was imparted, and they might be under ſuch Circumſtances, as your own reſolutions oft in print, would diſcharge from that Worſhip as a <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you may reply, that the reaſon of the Poſition gives no countenance to ſuch a reſtriction. And I ſay ſo too: but ſeeing they agree no better in your Edition, what muſt be done in the caſe? But to have recourſe firſt to the Errata, ay, &amp; to the Author too: but as you have ordered the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>non ſunt inventi</hi> is a good return; for the Author was, but is not, and the Errata never was, nor could be. And therefore in my Opinion, if the <hi>Poſition</hi> be of a better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance than the <hi>ground</hi> of it, let us take <hi>that;</hi> but if the <hi>Reaſon</hi> be of a righter make than the Poſition, let us take that for the Authors.</p>
            <p>The reaſon, as large as it is, is expreſly incluſive of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106428:14"/>Common-Prayer <hi>only;</hi> And therefore conſidering that all the Arguments are according to the Authors profeſſion, <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient</hi> to this Poſition; and the ground of it: and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are exuberant. or impertient: I conclude you had not ſufficient reaſon to ſay as you do, <hi>p.</hi> 2. of your Poſtſcript, <hi>That Dr.</hi> O. (or the Author) <hi>ſaith, that all Lyturgies, uſuch, are ſuch falſe Worſhip (and not the Engliſh only)</hi> no, nor to ſay that it was his <hi>meaning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But farther, I conceive the Author may not, yea, doth not mean by theſe words [becauſe "that Worſhip itſelf—is not lawful] that it is <hi>ſimply</hi> unlawful; which muſt render it ſo at all times, and to all Perſons, under what circumſtances ſoever: but that taken with all its modes, as well as matter, and the manner, ſeverity, and univerſality of its impoſing, it is ſo. Beſide, it is not ſaid that according to the rule of the Goſpel, it is <hi>unlawful</hi> but [according to the rule of the Goſpel it is not <hi>lawful</hi>] which may fairly be conſtrued thus. The rule of the Goſpel doth not authenticate, or <hi>warrant</hi> it: and I think ought to be ſo Conſtrued; it being the <hi>defect</hi> of that rule, not its <hi>oppoſition,</hi> which he lays the great ſtreſs of his Cauſe upon.</p>
            <p>A ſhort conſideration of your anſwer (hitherto) will ſuffice; becauſe you do not pretend <hi>therein</hi> to conſider his Poſition, but to lay down your own Poſitions (which I have already tranſcribed (and that's enough) <hi>and the Hiſtory of the matter of Fact, which muſt</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>be premiſed, for the right deciding of the cauſe:</hi> Which amount to the number of 25 heads. The firſt head I think very improperly called matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> at leaſt many particulars contained in it. From firſt to ſeventh, you give an account of ſome Forms Divinely preſcribed, which hath little, if any thing to do in the queſtion. And for the inſtances you give of what was done, impoſed, ſubmitted to; how far, and in what manner, by divers Perſons, in divers times, and of as diverſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances (which with the former take up full out <hi>four</hi> pages) I ſuppoſe will not not be greatly cogent to the men of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, without ſome Divine Precept, or Pattern expreſs, or implied. I may have leave therefore to procced to the Authors premiſes, and your replies.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106428:15"/>
               <p>Some things muſt be premiſed, to the confirmation of this Poſition.</p>
               <p>Firſt. The whole Syſtem of Lyturgical Worſhip, with all its inſeparable dependences, are intended: For (as ſuch) it is eſtabliſhed by Law (as ſuch) it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that we receive it, and attend unto it: It is not in our power, it is not left to our judgment, or liberty to cloſe with, or make uſe of any part, of it, as we ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>There are in the Maſs book many Prayers directed to God only by Jeſus Chriſt, yet it is not lawful for us thereon to go to Maſs, under a pretence only of joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in thoſe in thoſe lawful Prayers. As we muſt not affect their Drink-offerings of Blood, ſo we muſt not take up their names in our lips, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.4. Have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In your anſwer to this <hi>Premiſe,</hi> you ſay, p. 6. <hi>I ſhall now examine the Doctors Premiſes. To the firſt I anſwer,</hi> Firſt, <hi>If he will include all that is in the Lyturgy, the Nonconformiſts conſeſs that there is ſomewhat in it which they diſſent from as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſitſiable; and ſo there is in all mens Worſhip of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I cannot well tell who you mean here by the <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> which you contradiſtinguiſh from the perſons you oppoſe, you ſomewhere in this piece divide a ſort of men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and p. 29. I preſume the ſame concerned in your ranks of <hi>Worldly</hi> PR. IGs <hi>and the unruly</hi> PR. IG's for ſo uſual are theſe obliging terms with you, that you need not doubt but <hi>proud Ignorants</hi> will be eaſily ſpelt in theſe contracts. But we have Coiners enough of diſgraceful Titles, without the help of Perſons of your Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. I may gueſs freely that you put your ſelf, and thoſe <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> that jump juſt with you, in neither of theſe diviſions; but betwixt them, <hi>i. e.</hi> neither <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> nor <hi>Fanaticks:</hi> But there be enow will take the liberty of ſuch Coinage, and put you, and yours into the Cub with the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> and call the Conteſts between you, and thoſe you here oppoſe <hi>Bellum Fanaticale.</hi> But I muſt paſs from this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106428:15"/>dividing conceſſion, to your next words, containing (as you ſay) the Authors <hi>firſt Errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>He intimateth that it is not in our power to cloſe with ſome, and not with all: This is his firſt Errour,</hi> [which you ſcore up in the Margin, as I have done Error I. here; you prove it thus.] <hi>Though Man gives us no ſuch power, God doth; as it is in my power to believe all that one ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth truly: and well; and not that which he ſpeaketh amiſs. I am not bound to own all that any Preacher, or Prieſt ſhall ſay in the Church. God put it in the Diſciples power to beware of the leaven of the Scribes and Phariſees, and yet to hear them.</hi> Proving <hi>all things, is not</hi> approving <hi>all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, The Author doth not ſay what you charge on him as his Error; nor do you ſay that he ſaith it, only <hi>he intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> ſo much. And I cannot call this <hi>fair</hi> dealing; for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his words ſeem to you to intimate that Error, they may not ſo to him. And you know Sir, that many ſay ſuch words, who deny, and abhor that which others ſay, and <hi>know</hi> is the juſt ſenſe, or conſequence of the words they expreſs their minds in: But the Error you faſten on him is neither. Look again on the words that muſt intimate this Error, if any. <q>[It is not in our power, it is not left to our judgment, or liberty to cloſe with, or make uſe of any part of it as we ſhall think fit.]</q> I will not ſo much ſuſpect my Readers judgment, as to ſay any more to enlighten it.</p>
            <p>Yet ſuppoſe he had ſaid thoſe very words; the Friends of the Lyturgy I believe will conſent to them as true, and now I ſhall prove that you have not proved the contrary. You ſay, <hi>Though man gives us no ſuch power, God doth.</hi> But it is as plain as two and two makes four, that the Author <hi>aſſirms it</hi> of power, or <hi>liberty</hi> left us by the Law of men, and that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires complyance in all. I am ſorry I muſt be fain to repeat his words again, but that will ſuffice; and they are, <q>[For as ſuch it is eſtabliſhed by <hi>Law,</hi> and not in any <hi>part</hi> of it only; as ſuch it is <hi>required</hi> that we receive, and <hi>attend</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; it is not in our <hi>power,</hi> &amp;c.</q> And Sir, take this, and what follows of <hi>proving</hi> not to be <hi>approving:</hi> and our licenſe to diſtinguiſh what we hear: I humbly conceive they do not belong to the preſent queſtion, and that though proving, to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106428:16"/>
               <hi>diſcern</hi> the truth, is the duty (whatever be the <hi>power,</hi> a word eaſily miſtaken) of thoſe that hear, yet it is not the duty, or the liberty of thoſe that pray by a <hi>known Liturgy:</hi> that may, and ought to be proved <hi>before,</hi> and not to be a matter of doubt, when they might before-hand have put it <hi>out</hi> of doubt. I hope you have not forgot that you have ſaid this to be one benefit of a ſet, known Form, which a Miniſterial, Conceived, <hi>extempore</hi> prayer hath not. When men Preach, they bid us hear, and the Ear tries words, but when they pray, they bid us pray, and by the Lyturgy our Amen is required, and not our Opinion, or Scrutiny: In <hi>extempore</hi> prayers both are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to what is good. Your Author proceeds.</p>
            <p>
               <q>There are in the Maſs book many Prayers directed to God; only by Jeſus Chriſt; yet it is not lawful for us thereon to go to Maſs, under a pretence only of joyning in ſuch lawful prayers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>All this will be granted by all Proteſtants that I know of, but how far you render it ſhort of the Authors end, is now to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>You anſwer, <hi>Though the Maſs have many good prayers, the Corruption by twiſted Idolatry, and Hereſy, maketh Communion there unlawful. Heathens, and Turks have good Prayers. Prove any ſuch Hereſy, or Idolatry in the Church Worſhip by the Lyturgy, and we will avoid it: But if I may join in your own good prayers, and preaching, notwithſtanding your many failings, and ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as are here pleaded for, why not with others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reverend Sir, Reaſons againſt the ſtrength of this anſwer are, Firſt, The Maſs is not more twiſted in all the parts of it by Law, than the Lyturgy, nor left leſs to our power to pick and chuſe. If this union do render the far greater pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, the Idolatry, and Hereſy of the Maſs infectious to the whole Worſhip, who can prove that the pollutions of other Worſhip, where we are likewiſe commanded not to diſtinguiſh, or divide, doth not in their kind, and degree diffuſe the taint alike? Mental dividing, or culling by ſecret diſapprobation, and not joyning in our hearts, is all you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, unleſs you did allow (which you do not) Mr. <hi>Humph.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106428:16"/>Fens</hi> manner, to ſay <hi>aloud Amen</hi> to every Prayer of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, except the Prayer for the Biſhops, and to that to diſſent by a ſingular ſilence. Nor have you proved that no other ſin but Idolatry and Hereſy, may juſtify refuſing to Worſhip by the Maſs; nor that far leſs ſins than they may do it, nor that the Lyturgy hath not by ſome way or other ſuch ſin cleaving to it, as is like the Leproſy that could not be ſcraped; waſhed, or fired out.</p>
            <p>Your inſtance of <hi>Heathens, and Turks having good Prayers,</hi> is not a very good one. What good Prayers without faith in Chriſt? Though they may be prayers for ſome good thing: and you let drop this Weapon without any uſing it, for your oppoſites to take up; for whoſe purpoſe it ſerves much more than for yours. There is no parity of a word, or ſentence in a conceived prayer exceptionable, and the other intire, will all known, or doubtful circumſtances. All men are not, few men are to be compared with your ſelf for concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Prayer: yet a man may find many, whoſe failings in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do not pollute their Prayers; nor if they have Errours in their minds, do they put them into the words of their Prayers. Theſe things you have not obviated in your anſwer, which to me is not ſufficient to prove againſt the Authors Agrument, that men muſt not go to the Worſhip by the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, under a pretence only of joyning in ſuch lawful Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>
               <q>2d <hi>Premiſe.</hi> It is to be conſidered as Armed with Laws, (1.) Such as declare, and injoyn it as the only true Worſhip of the Church, (2.) Such as prohibit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, and puniſh all other ways of the Worſhip of God in Church Aſſemblies: By our Communion, and Conjunction in it, we juſtify thoſe Laws.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Error you charge your Author with, is <q>[That our Communion juſtifieth all Errour 2, the Laws that impoſe the Lyturgy, yea, the poenal ſeverities.]</q> 
               <hi>This.</hi> (you ſay) <hi>is too groſs an Errour to be wirtten with any ſhew of proof.</hi> You endeavour to prove the Errour ſuch, by inquiring, <hi>What if the Creed, or Lords Paryer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106428:17"/>were too rigorouſly impoſed—muſt we forbear them, or juſtify the Law?—then a rigorous Law-makes may take away our Chriſtian liberty</hi> (you might have ſaid as aptly our Chriſtian duty) <hi>by commanding us to uſe ſuch things ſo ſtrictly.</hi> p. 7.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Firſt. That you give us not the ſaid Errour in the Authors words formally. Secondly, That you add <hi>all</hi> the Laws, and the <hi>poenal ſeverities</hi> which are not to be found in the Author, and thereby ſtrain theſe words [We juſtify thoſe Laws] beyond their neceſſary ſenſe, for you turn an Indefinite into an Univerſal, <hi>all Laws,</hi> and the juſtification of each Law to the moſt diſtaſtful, and exceptionalbe part of it: And I doubt not to affirm, that doing that which a Law requires, ſo far as the intention is moved by the Law, is a juſtifying of it: And ſubmitting to any Law upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of its penalties, is ſo far a juſtifying its praeceptive part, as not ſo <hi>great</hi> an evil as the <hi>poenal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To your proof I ſay, that a duty, though impoſed by Laws, with penalties, remains a duty notwithſtanding: and you know that the Author doth not allow it to be a duty, whatever you do: &amp; he who doth that which is a duty, though not impoſed by a human Law, may, and ought to be ſuppoſed to do that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſimply as ſuch, unleſs he ſay the contrary: and therefore doth not at all juſtify the impoſing Law thereby; which reaches your Query fully: But your Author ſaith it of that, which none that I know ſay is a duty ſimply, or without any dependance upon human Sanctions; which makes a wide difference: for things of their own nature indifferent, and ſubmitted to as <hi>Commanded;</hi> this compliance muſt needs ſo far juſtify the very <hi>jus</hi> of the Law. As to the poenal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I ſpake before.</p>
            <p>Your Authors third Premiſe is, that, 3d <hi>Premiſe.</hi> 
               <q>This Conjunction in Communion, by the Worſhip of the Lyturgy, is the Symbol, pledge, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of an Eccleſiaſtical Incorporation with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in it's preſent Conſtitution. It is ſo in the Law of the Land. It is ſo in the Canons of the Church. It is ſo in the common underſtanding of all men; and by theſe Rules muſt our Profeſſion, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106428:17"/>Practice be judged, and not by any reſerve of your own; which neither God, nor good men will allow of.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, you firſt diſtinguiſh of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as an ambiguous word; which I muſt repeat, though you do not determine what it is. You ſay, pag. 8. it is ambiguous, I. <hi>As it ſignifieth a part of the univerſal Church, agreeing in Faith, one God, one Chriſt, and all eſſential to the Church.</hi> 2. <hi>And alſo as it is a Chriſtian Kingdom, under one King. 3. And as it is a Confederacy of many Churches to keep Concord in lawful Circumſtantials, as well as integrals. In all theſe ſenſes it is a lawful</hi> Aſſociation. I humbly conceive Sir, that your Reader is little edified by any of theſe diſtinctions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which do not ſo much as pretend to any definition of a Church ſpecifically diſtinct from the Univerſal: but reſolve it at laſt into that, which may be <hi>no Church</hi> at all; nor have any the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being ſo, <hi>ſoil, a lawful Aſſociation.</hi> Yet this ſerves your turn to induced an Errour of the Doctors thus, <hi>But if any Church go beyond theſe bounds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Errour 4.</note> 
               <hi>and on good pretences ſhall agrce upon any Errour or Evil, it is a miſtake to hold that, all that incorporate with them in the three foreſaid lawful reſpects; do therefore confederate with them in their Errour.</hi> This is your fourth Errour.</p>
            <p>Sir, I have ſearched narrowly into the Authors <hi>Premiſe,</hi> to find where he holds this Errour, or takes any notice, or hath any thing that ſenſes of the Church of <hi>England</hi> under all, or any of <hi>your</hi> three-fold reſpects; much leſs that he hold, <hi>That all that incorporate with them in thoſe reſpects, do therefore Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with them in their Errour.</hi> The third <hi>Premiſe</hi> to which you anſwer, is here before the Readers Eye, in which the Errour muſt be found, or no where. And if all the Eyes in the World, with the help of the moſt enlarging ſpectacles can find it there, I am content to forfeit mine own. I beſeech you Sir, doth the Author hold, or any man breathing, that to incorporate with a Chriſtian Kingdom under one King, is to Confederate with them in their Errour?</p>
            <p>But in your numeration finding this the fourth Errour, I bethought my ſelf that the laſt was branded with the ſecond
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106428:18"/>Errour; but do what I could, I found the fourth Errour next ſuccedding to ehe ſecond, and no ſuch thing as a third Errour with his mark on, nor without it. In ſhort Sir, (if you will bear with a very ſmall criticiſm) you <hi>miſtold</hi> the third Errour, and told the fourth very much amiſs, I cannot like this manner of inflaming <hi>such</hi> reckonings.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the fifth marked Errour, of which you ſay, p. <hi>9th.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Errour 5.</note> 
               <hi>It is therefore another of your miſtakes, that owning the Pariſh-Churches, and Worſhip, is an own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the preſent Dioceſan Conſtitution.</hi> By the way, I will tell my Reader, that though many have believed, and ſtifly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed otherwiſe, I never found any of your Words, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Works, countenancing the Form of a Dioceſan Church, or a Prelatical Hierarchy. I do not here determine of the Rectitude, or Errour of it: But I ſay it here, becauſe the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour charged, or the charging of it as ſuch, hath ſome influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from the fore mentioned hint.</p>
            <p>But to the purpoſe, I muſt ſay Sir, that the matter of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this ſaid Errour, hath ſome relation to the Authors <hi>premiſe;</hi> for a Dioceſan Conſtitution is a part of the preſent Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But for the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate which muſt contain what makes the Errour, if there be any, I can find no more of it than in the fomer, in all the words you ſay are the Author's premiſe. I beſeech you Sir, doth he ſay a word here of <hi>owning Pariſh-Churches,</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> or do Pariſh-Churches, taken ſtrictly in our Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe, find the Form, or Name of a Church? Do you not know, that only the Biſhop is the Paſtor, all other Prieſts or Miniſters but Curates? And if we try the ſtrength of your <hi>therefore;</hi> by which you prove it an Errour, it will amount to little more: It is this, <hi>But I further diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the many Pariſh-Churches, and the Dioceſan; and the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as conſtituted of ſuch Dioceſan Churches. The Old Non-conformists commonly owned the Pariſh-Churches, (and the Church of</hi> England <hi>as made up of such) but not the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan: This they openly profeſſed. It is therefore a miſtake, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did not expect ſuch manner of diſputing from Mr. <hi>B.</hi> You diſtinguiſh contrary to the Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical Laws and Conſtitutions; and the Old Non-conformiſts commonly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106428:18"/>owned your diſtinction, which diſtinction is a nulling of the Dioceſan Church, from which the Parochial is not only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, but ſeparated: It is therefore an Errour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is this proving <hi>per notiora,</hi> or <hi>obſcuriora?</hi> And all amounts to this: The Doctor, or Author hold that Errour which you cannot find the ſenſe of in the <hi>Premiſe,</hi> and you prove it by ſuch Arguments to be an Errour (if it were there) that none will take for <hi>unquestionable,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>unqueſtioned</hi> Verities; and therefore this fifth Errour may be wiped off with the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo it is your miſtake to ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">VI. Err.</note>
               <hi>that Communion by the Liturgy is the ſymbol and pledge of the foreſaid Incorporation into the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in its preſent Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the matter and form of this, I acknowledge you come nearer to the Authors words, than I have uſually found, tho not without ſome difference. But before I proceed, I muſt take leave to diſtinguiſh a little of <hi>Communion,</hi> thus:
<list>
                  <item>1. Communion by the Liturgy is either very rare, it may be but once, or twice, or ſo. This I do not take to be a ſymbol of the ſaid Incorporation; nor can you give any proof that it was the Authors meaning.</item>
                  <item>2. Or it may be conſidered as conſtant, and ſuch (taken ſtrictly) I know none, or very few that practiſe.</item>
                  <item>3. Or an ordinary Communion, ſuch as is more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, than with any, or all other Churches, contradiſtinct from the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And this practice, I think, ought to be underſtood as the Authors meaning: And ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it will be hard for you to prove, it is not ſuch a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol. You endeavour to prove it thus; <hi>The Rulers openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that they take multitudes to be none of their Church, who joyn in the Liturgy.</hi> I anſwer:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>What Rulers do you mean, Civil, or Eccleſiaſtical? Who, or how many of them, or when, and where did they declare this ſo openly, or ſecretly either? Do they not own all the Kings Subjects of <hi>England</hi> to be of their Church, if baptized, and not excommunicated? Yea, to the very Diſſenters <hi>de jure,</hi> and that they are ſtraglers from the Fold they belong to? Therefore they firſt admoniſh, then excommunicate them, if
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106428:19"/>contumacious. Your Argument therefore from the Rulers is but dark, <hi>&amp; gratis dictum:</hi> And I have prov'd it a miſtake.</p>
            <p>You tell us next what is the Symbol, <hi>And it is ſubſcribing, declaring, and ſwearing Obedience, which is the Symbol.</hi> Theſe are all your own words, and not one added. A <hi>Symbol</hi> I little expected from ſo learned, and intelligent a perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Symbol</hi> you give here, is the Symbol of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> or men in Orders: I hope you are not come to this on a ſudden, that only the Clergy are the Church; and if this be the Symbol, or badge of a Member incorporated into the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and no other; what becomes of the poor <hi>Laity?</hi> You have not forgotten ſure, that all this debate hath been, if not of the Communion of the Laity <hi>only,</hi> at leaſt of meer Lay-Communion. You add, <hi>Yea they excommunicate many that come to the Liturgy-ſervice.</hi> Some I confeſs but not very many, ſuppoſing the Office of the <hi>Communion,</hi> to be part of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> they come unto. And I ſhall add, that when they are excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, they come not, or more <hi>unwelcom,</hi> till they be declared abſolved. And I believe I may now have my intelligent, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Readers ſuffrage, to ſend this Errour after its fellows.</p>
            <p>Next Task is to conſider theſe <hi>Three</hi> Errours, which are all in a file; which thus in ſhort you expreſs.</p>
            <list>
               <item>VII Err. <hi>You miſtake when you ſay, It is ſo by the Law of the Land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII Err. <hi>You miſtake again, when you ſay, It is ſo by the Canon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IX Err. <hi>You miſtake, when you ſay, It is ſo in the common underſtanding of all.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>You put me almoſt to a ſtand to come thus faſt upon me; I begin to bethink my ſelf, If you or I be not miſtaken in the nature of a <hi>Symbol,</hi> as we had almoſt taken the Clergy for the only Church e'en now: I ſhall therefore ſpend a word or two in inquiring, what it may import: I find that it means a <hi>ſign</hi> or <hi>badge</hi> to know <hi>one by</hi> from <hi>another;</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Colours</hi> which Souldiers wear in their Hats, or the <hi>white</hi> Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs about their Arms in nightly Encounters, to know <hi>friends</hi> from <hi>foes</hi> by: And I think our <hi>Creed,</hi> called the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (I knew not well <hi>why,</hi> except becauſe it is a Compoſure <hi>worthy</hi> of ſuch Authors, or the number of its Articles being juſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106428:19"/>Twelve as theirs) is therefore in the Latine called <hi>Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Apoſtolorum,</hi> becauſe it contains ſo exactly the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of the Chriſtian Faith (or at leaſt hath been ſo eſteemed) that you may know a Chriſtian by it, from another man. Now Sir. I ſhall go on, and begin where I ended, at the <hi>9th</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <q>[<hi>It (ſcil.)</hi> Communion by the Liturgy, is the <hi>Symbol</hi> of the Incorporation aforeſaid, in the common Opinion of <hi>all.</hi>]</q> And if you take the <hi>all,</hi> not for all <hi>men,</hi> Heathen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor all in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or Church of <hi>England,</hi> of which many know nothing of a Symbol at all, but of Chriſtians in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or elſewhere, any thing acquainted with the matter in hand: I believe our Authors <hi>Errour</hi> will prove a <hi>Truth,</hi> in the <hi>common</hi> Opinion. We cannot bring it to the <hi>Poll,</hi> and therefore being brought thus far, muſt leave it to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders judgment; but if any differ from me, or the truth <hi>ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> matter, I ſhall not think it worthy to be ſcored up in Capital Figures, for one of his Errours.</p>
            <p>If I prove that the foreſaid Communion is the <hi>Symbol</hi> of a Memberſhip in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in its <hi>preſent</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, both by the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and by the <hi>Canons;</hi> then the Author is not guilty of theſe <hi>two</hi> Errours you charge him with, and they will be returned upon your <hi>ſelf</hi> as two of your own <hi>miſtakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope you will not ſay when you think better of it, that a man may be a Member of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at the <hi>preſent,</hi> and yet not a Member of it in its preſent <hi>Conſtitution</hi> (though you ſeem to ſay ſo;) for then a man muſt be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that which <hi>is not:</hi> unleſs you believe it hath <hi>one</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution for ſome, <hi>another</hi> for others. The Conſtitution of it is the ſame, though the Memberſhip is different; ſo that Perſon who is a <hi>Lay-Member,</hi> is not obliged for that Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> for <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>as ſuch;</hi> yet the difference lies not in the Conſtitution of the Church, which is made up of all the parts, in the order, and manner preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; but in the ſtation of each Perſon, according to that <hi>one</hi> Conſtitution. In ſhort, whatever <hi>different</hi> ſtation Perſons may have therein, Communion by the Worſhip of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy is neceſſary to their <hi>Memberſhip,</hi> (which is the queſtion) and without it there can be no Member of one ſort or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106428:20"/>
            <p> The Law makes it the <hi>Symbol; for</hi> if the queſtion be put whether any Worſhip be according to the uſage of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is not <hi>Sermons,</hi> nor private <hi>Conceived</hi> Prayers will be taken for ſuch, without the uſe of the Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: But the uſe of the Lyturgy will be ſo accepted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Sermon, or Conceived Prayers. I can tell you of a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> Convicted in <hi>Kent,</hi> which was kept on a <hi>Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> in the Pariſh-Church; and all becauſe the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> was not read at that time, and place. Recuſancy depends on the obſervation of the Lyturgy; and no other part of Worſhip. This <hi>alone</hi> is called the ſervice of the Church either in <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>Canon,</hi> and is therefore <hi>preſcribed</hi> to be done in a Surplice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which none of the other parts of Worſhip are by <hi>Law</hi> to be honoured with. He that attends not to this, is l able to Excommunication, by Law, and anon; he that is Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate for this, or other Crimes, muſt not be admitted to <hi>this</hi> Communion, nor to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> burial, <hi>i. e.</hi> in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated ground, or any where elſe, by the Office of Burial in the Lyturgy, read over his Corps, and Grave.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will require proof of all this by Citations, though I think their mention is enough, to all that pretend to any inſight into Law, or Canons. However I ſhall comply. The Acts <hi>Primo I lizab. Decino quarto Caroli Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> obdlige all to it according to the Lyturgy; which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by entred in matter, and form into the very body of the Law. Theſe are the <hi>preceptive</hi> parts of the Law, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the whole to every Member, and no other but Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: for ſuch theſe Laws will have all the Kings <hi>Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born.</hi> Subjects in this Kingdom to be.</p>
            <p>The Canons oblige to the <hi>ſame,</hi> by puniſhing all that ſhall ſpeak againſt, or <hi>inpugn</hi> all, or any part of the Liturgical Communion, or relatives to it as ſuch, with Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> Canon 3.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. and Cannon 9. all that <hi>ſeparate</hi> from Communion by the <hi>Lyturgy,</hi> and count ſuch as Conform, unmeet to join with, and combine in a new Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood, are to be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto.</hi> And Can. 13. obliges to a total obſervation of <hi>Lyturgical</hi> ſervice, to all Perſons within the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and the Canons are ſaid to be eſtabiliſhed by Law. I hope I have ſaid enough to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106428:20"/>bring off theſe two ſaid Errours from that Character. Now Sir, I pray conſider, that I have concerned my ſelf in my inquiry as far as to your <hi>9th</hi> Errour on the Doctors ſcore, and have ſaid ſomewhat to all (except the third, which was not in your Catalogue) in order, without picking, or culling; and I believe you <hi>your ſelf</hi> will ſee cauſe at leaſt to <hi>doubt,</hi> that you have too poſitively, and raſhly imputed theſe Errours, both for matter, and form, on the worthy Doctor deceaſed: who had he ſurviv'd your Print, he would not have needed ſuch a ſilly Advocate as I. But you knew he was <hi>dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have done my main work, intended to the demoliſhing of that <hi>hard-favoured</hi> Monument, you had erected over his grave, and fame: And in its <hi>room,</hi> I ſhall give my Reader a <hi>true,</hi> though <hi>defective</hi> Character of him.</p>
            <p>He was a Perſon whoſe Learning, Parts, and Piety, ſilled not only this Iſland, but alſo many other parts of the world, with the <hi>acceptable</hi> ſound of his name. His Learning was <hi>univerſal,</hi> deep, and ſolid in his early days: which raiſed him to the ſtations of Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Vice-Chancellor of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity;</hi> which he was Elected to (and held divers years ſucceſſively) when he wanted ſome years of the Age of Forty; a very rare example. And though his Years, Piety, Principles, and <hi>ſtrait</hi> Diſcipline, with the intereſt he adhered to, affected many of the Heads, and Students with <hi>Contempt, Envy,</hi> and Enmity at the <hi>firſt,</hi> his <hi>Perſonal Worth,</hi> Obliging Deportment, and Dexterity in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs that concerned him in <hi>that</hi> Station, ſo Maſtered <hi>all,</hi> that the Univerſity grew not only content with, but proud of ſuch a Vice-Chancellor. And indeed ſuch were his Temper and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, that whatever Station, or ſort of Men, his Lot, Choice, or Intereſt ſhould place him in, or among; it would be no <hi>ſmall</hi> wonder if he were not uppermoſt: <hi>that</hi> was his <hi>proper</hi> ſphere, which thoſe with whom he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, generally <hi>Cour<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> him into, and few envied, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived. He was an excellent, and ſound Writer; his Works many, ſome large; wherein he dived beyond <hi>moſt</hi> into the <hi>leſs</hi> obvious parts of Learning: yet was he ſo great an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> that for Matter, Manner, and Efficacy on the Hearers, he repreſented <hi>indeed</hi> an Embaſſador of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106428:21"/>moſt High, a Teacher of the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God. His Perſon, &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment were ſo <hi>gentile,</hi> &amp; graceful, that rendred him, when <hi>preſent,</hi> as <hi>affecting,</hi> or more, than his Works, and Fame, when abſent; this advanced the luſtre of his internal Excellencies, by ſhining through ſo <hi>bright</hi> a Lanthorn. No wonder the then <hi>regnant</hi> Party Courted him, or that his Happineſs ſhould prove his Temptation. He was indeed ſometimes a little <hi>Impatient</hi> of Contradiction (the common Companion of high Eſteem) yet on <hi>Cool</hi> Thoughts, or the conviction of <hi>Experience,</hi> he would pay the greater Reſpects to thoſe, who freely, and faithfully expreſſed themſelves; he was not Nice of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Honour, and Reſpects from others; yet as free to return them, where they were deſerved. He had indeed an <hi>humble</hi> Loftineſs, and a <hi>loſty</hi> Humility. His exerciſes by <hi>Afflictions</hi> were very great, in reſpect of his <hi>Children,</hi> none of which he <hi>much</hi> injoyed while living, and ſaw them all go off the Stage before him: In reſpect of <hi>ſickneſſes,</hi> very long, langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and often ſharp and violent, like the blows of <hi>inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> death, yet was he both calm, and ſubmiſs under all; In reſpect of the ſtate of Chriſts <hi>Church,</hi> it lay ſo <hi>near</hi> his Heart, that if he were led to any thing that looked like too <hi>ſudden,</hi> or <hi>extreme,</hi> it might rationally be imputed to <hi>that.</hi> His general frame was ſerious, cheerful, and diſcourſive; his expreſſions ſavouring nothing of Diſcontent, much of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and love to Chriſt, and Saints, and all Men, which came from him ſo ſeriouſly, and <hi>ſpontaneouſly,</hi> as if Grace and Nature were in him reconciled, and but one thing. In a word, whatever he was, a mean could not contain him. Take him altogether, he excelled as a Man, a Chriſtian, a Scholar, a Divine, and a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>Sir, I have now done with what concerns Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> I have been upon the defenſive part of his Name and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which you have aſſaulted (unſeaſonably, to ſay no more) and who hath greater concerns to mind then ſuch pitiful ſcuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles as theſe, if they were within his reach. And when I read, and conſidered that <hi>ingenuous</hi> acknowledgment of your infirmities, <hi>Poſtſcr.</hi> p. 5. your loſs, and diſeſteem of reputation, p. 13. (which I will not recite, becauſe ſome may make worſe conſtructions of it) wherein I believe you have in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106428:21"/>your Hamility, and <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> as much overſhot againſt your ſelf, as you ſeem at other times againſt others whom you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: I cannot but after all <hi>diſlikes,</hi> continue in the ſame perfect Charity, and reſpects for you, as formerly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in the ſincerity of what you ſay, <hi>ſcil.</hi> That though your writings contain ſome expreſſions that ſeem over-ſharp, <hi>you can bear twice as much from others;</hi> which is a great, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted patience. I hope I have not taken a liberty ſo far to try it, which would ill become me, and I am ſure I have taken no incouragement from this, your <hi>more</hi> than good natur'd indulgence.</p>
            <p>After all that hath been ſaid by you in the diſcourſe above conſidered, I perceive your <hi>drift</hi> is (and I think you will ſay I am not miſtaken) not to aſſert Lyturgical Worſhip to be <hi>abſolutely</hi> neceſſary, as you <hi>manifeſtly oppoſe</hi> thoſe, and only thoſe who affirm it to be <hi>ſimply</hi> unlawful: which it cannot be, if ever it was, or can be lawful to <hi>any;</hi> which is the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of your words, p. 2. of your <hi>Poſtſcript. Whereas I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten over, and over; that I perſuade no man either to, or from a publick Church, 'till I know his Circumſtances: And that I doubt not but it is one mans duty, and another mans ſin.</hi> I believe, Dear Sir, that tho this conceſſion may diſpleaſe thoſe who may beſt bear it, it may reconcile you to moſt of thoſe who are called Diſſenters. And you ſay alſo, p. 46. of the book, <hi>Let it be noted, that it is not all, nor the greateſt objections, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, which I here deal with;</hi> [<hi>ſcil.</hi> in the 12 Arguments] <hi>having done it elſewhere.</hi> Some of which you inſtance in, and others may be added; but how far they will go in the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, I ſhall not, I muſt not ſay. We live not in the days of <hi>Trajan,</hi> when every man might think what he <hi>pleaſed,</hi> and ſpeak what he thought; and it may be, ſuch a liberty would neither be fir, nor ſafe. And if (as you allow) the practical determination depends on the Circumſtances of the perſons, you reduce the Controverſy to a far narrower room, than was by many ſuppoſed. And every one being beſt capable of underſtanding his own Circumſtances, it will not bear great heat, or importunity from another: This I ſay, as <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad hominem.</hi> I know Sir, how apt our natures are to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and to partial, unconſidered Animoſities againſt thoſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106428:22"/>who do not <hi>juſt jump</hi> with us in our Opinions, and every mean to their intereſt; ſuch mean Spirits are we of! Whatever others do, or ſay, or think, I <hi>deſire</hi> to love <hi>all</hi> men, with a love of <hi>benevolence,</hi> and that which is good in all men, with a proportional love of Approbation, and Complacence: To carry it with a ſpecial love, and reſpect, to all that fear God, though not in <hi>all</hi> things, nor in <hi>many</hi> things of my perſuaſion: yea, to hold Church-Communion with them as far as the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel allows, &amp; no farther; chuſing Love, Peace, Communion for their <hi>own</hi> ſakes, and for Chriſts ſake: but Debates, and epara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any degree, only for <hi>neceſſity</hi> ſake, and as a leſs evil than <hi>ſin:</hi> To keep cloſe to the Principles I profeſs in mine <hi>own Practice,</hi> to be Charitable, and Peacable, and not unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably Cenſorious, and troubleſome to thoſe who believe, and practiſe different from me: To have mental Communion with all the Members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> throughout the world; and whatever any of their Carriages may be to me, to love, and ſpeak as well of them, as conſiſts with Truth, or <hi>warranted</hi> Charity, whether they <hi>will</hi> accept of it, or <hi>not.</hi> Now the God of the Spirits of all fleſh, diſpoſe the hearts of Rulers, and <hi>Ruled,</hi> of what Degree, or Station <hi>ſoever,</hi> effectually, and <hi>practically</hi> to know their <hi>reſpective</hi> Duties, and <hi>therein</hi> the things that belong to their preſent, and everlaſting Peace.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let every Man prove his own Work, and ſo ſhall he have rejoycing in himſelf, and not in another,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>P. 4. l. 35. for <hi>an,</hi> read <hi>the. ibid.</hi> l. 36. blot out from the the word <hi>ſent,</hi> to the word <hi>alſo,</hi> l. 39. theſe 3 lines being obſcure. p. 5. l. 8. read <hi>who you ſay Chid.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
